So today's daf is כ"א Khaf Aleph 21. We pick up in
the middle of כ"א עמוד ב' Khaf Amud Bet and we are
or actually not the middle, the top of כ"א עמוד ב', Khaf
Amud Bet, we're a bit behind, and we pick up with the
בעי מיניה Ba'ei Minei four lines from the top. So, and we're
dealing with the different materials on which a גט Get can be
written, and we dealt with what defines an act of writing and
inscribing does constitute an act of writing if you're actually working on
the letters themselves rather than on pushing down or cutting away the
surrounding material. בעי מיניה רבא מרב נחמן. Ba'ei Minei Rava me-Rav Nachman.
רבא Rava asked רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. כותב על הגט טס של
זהב. Kosev al ha-get tass she-zahav. So you wrote a גט Get
on a gold plate, on a gold like whatever. What's a טס?
Tass? So like anyway, some type of a of a of gold
foil. ואמר לה התקבלי גיטך והתקבלי כתובתך. Va-amar la hiskabli giteich v'hiskabli
kesuvoseich. And actually the piece that you've of gold that you've written
it on is very valuable. It's gold. So when you gave it
to her you said here's your גט Get and here's your כתובה.
Kesuva. The value of the gold constitutes my payment for your כתובה.
Kesuva. So מהו? Mahu? What's the הלכה? Halakha? Does that count as
a giving of a גט? Get? So אמר לה התקבלי גיטך והתקבלי
כתובתך. Amar la hiskabli giteich v'hiskabli kesuvoseich. Yeah, it's a good גט
Get and the כתובה's Kesuva paid off. So what's the question at
stake? The question at stake, as we're going to see, is that
since the value of the material, the physical object, is considered to
be the payment of the כתובה, Kesuva, does it also count as
the giving of the גט? Get? And that has to do with
the issue we raised yesterday because how much is the giving of
the גט Get the transferring of the value of the object versus
the taking possession of an object of value, or is it just
the physical handing over of the object? If you remember yesterday we
said that even if the object was worth less than a פרוטה,
Pruta, was a leaf of an olive tree, or even if we
were dealing with what do you call it, a something that was
איסורי הנאה Issurei Hana'ah that had no value, and maybe by איסורי
הנאה Issurei Hana'ah even possibly not only of zero value but maybe
something that can't even be possessed, it nevertheless constitutes a giving of
a גט Get because physically the object was handed over. So here
the question is is that how about this? This is a case
where yes it was actually taken possession by the woman but the
act of taking possession was an act of was you know was
in a different context in which like you know than the than
the actual receiving of the גט. Get. One was in order to
take sort of to acquire its monetary value and maybe that redefines
the very nature of the act. So if you take a look
at תוספות Tosafos he says התקבלי גיטך והתקבלי כתובתך מהו. Hiskabli giteich
v'hiskabli kesuvoseich mahu. תוספות Tosafos says אף על גב דכתבו באיסורי הנאה
כשר. Af al gav d'kasvo be-issurei hana'ah kasher.
So we see clearly that you don't have to take it doesn't
have to be value. So if there doesn't have to be value
to the object why can't the value of the object go towards
the כתובה? Kesuva? How does that make it any worse? If the
גט Get doesn't have to be of any value at all, let
the גט Get be of value and the value go towards the
payment of the כתובה. Kesuva. תוספות Tosafos says no. האי משום דיהיב
לה מיהא כל הגט. Hai mishum d'yehav la miah kol ha-get.
But there there's only one thing that's happening is that the object
is going over and it's all being given as a גט. Get.
אבל הכא לא יהיב לה אלא טופסא. Aval hacha lo yehav la
ela tofsa. Here you know fundamentally if you have a ten thousand
dollar גט Get and you're giving it over and you're focusing on
the value and the value should be the paying off of the
כתובה, Kesuva, it might be hard to view this as also the
giving of a גט. Get. Fundamentally we would view this as taking
the possession of the value of the object and the transferring of
an object of value and maybe that redefines the nature of the
act. So he says it does not. התקבלי גיטך והתקבלי כתובתך. Hiskabli
giteich v'hiskabli kesuvoseich. Both things can be happening here. So איתיבי Eiseivei
says the גמרא Gemara asks on this. התקבלי גיטך והשאר לכתובתך. Hiskabli
giteich ve-hashar le-kesuvoseich.
If somebody says to a woman here here's a object the גט
Get again was written I don't know on the side of a
car or was written on a piece of gold and take your
גט Get and any the part of this object that is the
גט Get isn't written on sort of the margins that'll go to
paying off your כתובה. Kesuva. Okay. So then the הלכה Halakha is
התקבלי גיטך והשאר לכתובתך. Hiskabli giteich ve-hashar le-kesuvoseich. It works. The גט
Get is a good גט Get and the margins of this like
piece of gold pays off the כתובה. Kesuva. So the גמרא Gemara
says טעמא דאיכא שאר. Taima d'ika shar.
That's only because there are margins. But if it was actually you
needed the actual area of the גט Get itself to be the
payment of the כתובה Kesuva that presumably would redefine the nature of
the act. דאיכא שאר הא ליכא שאר לא. D'ika shar ha leka
shar lo.
So it sounds like if there was no remnant, if there was
no margins
then the the thing and the גט Get itself was to pay
off the כתובה Kesuva it would not work as a giving of
a גט. Get. So the גמרא Gemara says no. הוא הדין אף
על גב דליכא שאר. Hu hadin af al gav d'leka shar. You
know what? That's not true. It would work even if there was
no margin. Okay. And the get the whole גט Get was also
the כתובה. Kesuva. So why did it give the example of margins?
והא קמשמע לן דאף על גב דאיכא שאר. Va-haka mashmalan de-af al
gav d'ika shar. That even if there is margins אי אמר לה
אין אי לא לא. Ee amar la in lo la. That if
only the it only counts as a paying of a כתובה Kesuva
if he said to her and the and the the rest of
it the margins goes for the כתובה. Kesuva. But if not, if
he didn't say anything to her he said here's your גט Get
and it was written on gold he couldn't say okay but give
me back the margins. I only gave you the גט Get part.
The margins no. He wouldn't be able to say that. If he
didn't say anything and specify that it was כתובה kesubah payment, she'd
be entitled to keep it all. Why? Because מאי טעמא mai ta'ama
אדעתא דמגילתא הוא, ada'ata d'megilta hu,
because it is the air space of the מגילה megillah and of
the scroll, and it's all considered to be of one piece, you
know, so therefore he can't say, oh no no, I only gave
you the part that the letters were written on but the space
between the lines and the space on the margins, that I was
keeping. You can't make that claim if you don't specify otherwise, it's
all one unit, okay. But if he does make the claim, I'm
keeping the margins or I'm going to use the margins to pay
off the כתובה, kesubah, that's a legitimate claim. But if you for
that's to teach you that you have to make the claim, otherwise
she's entitled to it. Okay, on the other hand, if you want
to ask what can be a good גט, get, you can actually
have that the whole value of the object of the גט get
goes towards the payment of the כתובה kesubah and it doesn't redefine
the nature of the act. Okay, so what we actually have now
is a lot of גמרות gemaras pointing towards the idea that the
giving of the גט get is not just an aspect of a
sort of קנין kinyan and transferring of possession, that the גט get
can be worth less than a פרוטה, perutah, could be worth zero,
maybe even as we discussed yesterday, maybe איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah is
even not able to be owned at all. So therefore the taking
of the גט get is not the taking of possession of the
גט, get, it's just the taking of the sort of physical having
it physically given over, even if there's no sort of הלכתי, halachic,
you know, sort of דיני ממונות dinei mamonous ownership and taking of
possession to the point that you can actually have two completely different
acts going on here: the physical giving of the גט get counts
as the גט get and the taking of possession of it counts
as the payment of the כתובה. kesubah. Yeah, you had a question.
Okay, yeah, Charlie.
Yes, today in practice, do we write גט get on קלף klaf
or on paper?
On קלף. klaf. I mean, but you could write them on paper.
Sure, you could even write it on a leaf of a tree,
yeah.
Because the קלף klaf actually has some value whereas a single sheet
of paper— Exactly.
I mean, when the גמרא gemara says not value, it's talking about
the case about the leaf of the tree, but right, a single
sheet of paper would be a perfect example, clearly worth worth less
than a penny, but a קלף klaf definitely is an object of
value. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara says like this: תנו רבנן,
tanu rabanan, הרי זה גיטך והנייר שלי, harei ze gittech vehaniyar sheli,
אינה מגורשת. eina megureshes. Now, given that we're dealing with this division,
let's say he says, here's your גט, get, but I get to
get but the paper is mine, I'm never giving over the paper.
She's not divorced. Now, again, that is different than a case of
איסורי הנאה. issurei hana'ah. איסורי הנאה, issurei hana'ah, she doesn't take ownership
of the paper, nobody can own the paper, but she fully takes
possession— I mean, there's nothing to own, but it's fully under her
control and her possession and he certainly doesn't have any rights to
it either. Okay, whereas here, by claiming that he's retaining ownership, what
he's also doing is he's not fully giving it over to her.
So that obviously makes it a very of a different nature than
איסורי הנאה. issurei hana'ah.
So, והנייר שלי, vehaniyar sheli, אינה מגורשת, eina megureshes, על מנת שתחזירי
לי את הנייר הרי זו מגורשת. al menat shetachziri li es haniyar
harei zu megureshes. But on the condition that you return the paper
to me, it is, because then it's a the giving over, it's
fully hers. She just now has to at some future time give
it back to him. That's like a תנאי, tnai, that's on the
condition that you give me a hundred dollars. So even though it
means that she won't get to keep the גט get in her
possession for forever, the act of giving is a complete act. It's
sort of like a מתנה על מנת להחזיר. matana al menat lehachzir.
You know, but the act of giving is, it's now fully under
her possession, and therefore she is divorced.
Okay, בעי רב פפא. bai rav pappa. So Rav Pappa asked: בין
שיטה לשיטה בין תיבה לתיבה מאי? bein shita l'shita bein teiva l'teiva
mai? Let's say he says, here's the גט, get, but I retain
but I'm retaining ownership and possession of the not of the space
on which the letters are written, but I'm retaining ownership over the
white space that exists between the letters and between the lines. Okay,
so is that still considered like he's giving her a גט get
if the paper of the white space between the words and the
lines remains his, and between the letters. So the גמרא gemara says:
תיקו. teiku. So we're not clear. Is that considered a real giving
of a גט? get? On the one hand, she gets the actual,
you know, or full, you know, besides the physical possession of it,
even the ownership— his ownership is only holding back the paper that's
the letters aren't written on, so maybe that's not considered a holding
back of the גט get itself. On the other hand, if you
imagine what would happen if you were to take the paper that
the letters weren't written on, then the whole thing would fall apart
and it would be these tiny little pieces of paper. So can
you really consider that to still be a גט? get? So that's
presumably the גמרא gemara ספק. safek. If he says על מנת al
menat that the external margins are mine, you know, you know, the
top and bottom and left and right margins are mine, obviously that
would be good, that would be like השאר לכתובתה. hashar l'kesubasah. But
in this case, if you imagine that he's only giving her a
stuff, you know, he has, if you imagine the piece of paper
is divided between the part that's hers and the part that's his,
right, if this
is whoever
what's left out the marker.
Anyway.
Anyway,
okay, so if you imagine, right,
that if you looked at it, what we actually need is two
colors. So if you can go to the, my board there on
the right side, you'll see markers. So if you imagine that you
have the document, right, and it was
like א ב ג ד alef beis gimmel dalet whatever, הרי את
מותרת.
harei at
miteret.
Really?
Go one step down, no, no, one board down, on the right
hand side, there's no, no, nope, nothing there. Anyway, alright, whatever. Okay,
so anyway,
moving on. Alright, I was certain I had a multi-colored marker there.
Okay, thank you. Alright, so anyway, so if you imagine, right, that
basically, right, his part of the document is like, well, whatever,
you know, I'm trying to see how to draw it, like this
is all his part of the document, right, right, all of this
is his, and her parts, right, are like, you know, are like
the, right, like, you know, all of this is his,
right, and, you know, this is, the red is his, oops, right,
anyway, if
you imagine that, right, so if that's the document, "Yeah, I'm giving
you the גט get and I'm keeping everything else." So like what
type of a גט get is it that has those tiny little
things that are not even connected to one another? So that's the
גמרא's Gemara's question which is, is that still like he's giving her
a גט? get?
So it says, the black גט get and the white גט, get,
like the black by the...
alright, exactly, the black by the wife. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara
says, okay, תיקו. teiku. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, וליחוש
דלמא ספרא אחד רחמנא ולא שנים ושלשה ספרים. v'lichush dilma safra echad
Rachmana v'lo shnayim u'shlosha sfarim. How about the fact though that
the גמרא Gemara says this should be obvious because based on, you
know, what we've sort of had exact thing,
that what she's left with is multiple pieces of paper and a
גט get has to be one singular object. So the גמרא Gemara
says,
לא צריכא דמעורה. lo tzricha dime'ura. The case is that the letters
are written in a way in which they are interwoven. What does
that mean? Or they're sort of connected, which is that basically if
you have a word here, right,
if you have I don't know, a whatever, let's say you have
a ד dalet here and then on the bottom line you've got
a ל lamed like that, okay, so therefore in this case, right,
if the, even if you were to cut out this area here,
right, you would have to stop at the ל lamed and you
cut out this area, so this would still sort of be, it
would all be sort of connected as it were in that case.
Now the funny, the thing is though, that would only, that you
can't do that with every single word. You can only do that
like you can connect lines, but he still said בין תיבה לתיבה.
bein teiva l'teiva. He didn't just say בין שיטה לשיטה. bein shita
l'shita. If you just cut out the space between the lines and
then it all sort of remains connected, right, because some line somehow
invades the space of the previous word, at least when you're done
with the cutting out, you do have one physical unit. But he
also said בין תיבה לתיבה, bein teiva l'teiva, between each word. It's
not only going to be possible to get it so that right
you, so I don't exactly get how that really fully solves the
problem. And anyway, what I also don't get is that if you
really successfully have made it in a way that even if you
were to cut out his space it would all be one unit,
so then I'm not sure why it's a תיקו, teiku, then why
shouldn't it work? Right? If you actually did write it on a
type of a
document with a lot of holes and gaps or whatever, but it
was one physical object, it's not clear to me why it shouldn't
work. So I don't really get it.
Right. Okay. Anyway,
I mean רש"י Rashi says, if you look at רש"י, Rashi, דמעורה,
dime'ura, מעורה במקצת שהיו בו אותיות ארוכות המגיעות משיטה לשיטה בראש כל
תיבה ותיבה. me'ura b'miktzat she'hayu bo otiyot arukot hamagi'ot mishita l'shita b'rosh
kol teiva v'teiva. So רש"י Rashi actually says that it invades every
single word. So I guess for רש"י Rashi maybe it would be
for every single, I don't know how you would have it unless
you didn't even wait for ל, lamed, you did it intentionally for
everything. So if you had the word here הרי את מותרת, harei
at miteret, I'm trying to think about it, הרי את מותרת, harei
at miteret,
how would you do it? And you said, so you would do
like לכל, l'chol,
that'd be interesting that that would be kosher, right, and then you
did I don't know, לכל אדם l'chol adam or something like this,
so that even if you were to try to cut out the
space between the words, you would still somehow have it all connected.
Anyway, somehow that's, anyway whatever it would be, but the point is
if it was constructed like that, it's straight, then what's the ספק?
safek? Then fine, then you take הנייר שלי haniyar sheli and you
still have a remaining thing that's a kosher גט. get. Anyway, take
a look at תוספות, Tosafot, but the גמרא Gemara leaves it as
a תיקו. teiku. Take a look at
תוספות Tosafot which תוספות Tosafot says, לא צריכא דמעורה. lo tzricha dime'ura.
תוספות Tosafot says like this,
מכאן דקדק רבנו יצחק בר מרדכי דאין צריך בגט. mikan dikdek Rabbeinu
Yitzchak bar Mordechai d'ein tzarich b'get. So here's a question: does every
letter have to have white space around it? Can letters be touching?
Okay, so he says כמאן דאמר הכא דמעורות. keman d'amar hacha de-meurot.
So he assumes what דמעורות de-meurot means is because he says, okay
big deal, if so, but so what if you have your למ"ד
lamed sticking up? If you just get out your scissors, you can
still cut around it, right? So how does that prevent you from
making everything fall apart? The only way this prevents you from making
it all apart into separate little scraps of paper is if the
letters are actually touching. But if the letters aren't touching, just get
a good enough razor and you could still cut out each word
individually. So he assumes that the דמעורות de-meurot means that the letters
are actually touching. But הריב"ם ha-Ribam says דאין כאן ראיה, de-ein kan
raya, דהאי דקאמר דמעורות d'hai d'ka'amar de-meurot היינו רגל כ"ף hainu regel
kaf של שיטה עליונה shel shita elyona בטי"ת be-tet של שיטה שמתחתיה
shel shita she-me-tachteiha או למ"ד בה"א o lamed be-heh או בחי"ת o
be-chet דלמעלה הימנה. de-lemala heimena. Okay. So he says no, as long
as it's like inside of a letter where we wouldn't cut around
it, alright? But it doesn't have to be touching and it's not
so clear that if it's touching it's okay. But then he says
מכל מקום דהוה ליה דאין צריך ראיה להכשיר mikol makom de-hava lei
de-ein tzarich raya lehachsher דדווקא בספר תורה de-davka be-Sefer Torah do we
need it that there's white space around. Alright, so there's an interesting
question, can the letters be touching? But anyway, the other interesting question
that I've got just about this גמרא Gemara is is that if
you've really constructed it in a way in which it's impossible that
even after you've cut out the husband's paper, it would still remain
one unit, then I don't know why it shouldn't be good. And
if it's constructed in a way that it can't remain one unit,
I don't know why it is good. So I'm not exactly still
sure what the ספק safek is that the גמרא Gemara feels it
can't answer. Anyway, we move on. Okay. בעי רמי בר חמא. Ba'i
Rami Bar Chama. רמי בר חמא Rami Bar Chama asked. היו מוחזקין
בעבד שהוא שלו וגט כתוב על ידו והרי הוא
יוצא מתחת ידה. Hayu muchzakim be'eved she'hu shelo veget kasuv al yado
ve'harei hu yotze mitachas yada. They knew that the slave was his
and you had a גט get written on the slave's arm and
now she's in possession of the slave, okay? מהו? Mahu? What's the
הלכה? halacha? Now we know from the משנה Mishna that you can
write on a slave and give the slave, but that's when there's
witnesses that it was given over. Here there's no witnesses, she's just
physically in possession of the slave. מהו? Mahu? מי אמרינן אקנויי אקניה
לה Mi amrinan akneiye aknei lah that he transferred possession of the
slave to her, או דילמא הוא מנפשיה אזל? o dilma hu minafshei
azal? Maybe the slave just figured out that he would rather live
with the woman than the man, you know, and he himself walked
over and she doesn't and the fact that the slave is in
her house is no evidence that it was actually transferred. Now that
seems to be a general question about how do you prove, you
know we normally say possession is not nine tenths, ten tenths of
the law, alright? That if you're possessing something you're assumed to be
the owner of it, but would we say that by a slave
that can actually just travel on his own? So that doesn't seem
to be a גט get question, it seems to be a general
question of ownership, of whether it's evidence of ownership. So the גמרא
Gemara says, so what's the הלכה? halacha? So אמר רבא ותיפוק ליה
דכתבא שיכול להזדייף. Amar Rava vetipokei lei dechsav sheyachol lehizayef. So before
even getting to that, רבא Rava says, I don't get it, if
you just wrote it on ink on the slave's arm, that could
be forged because you could erase it and write something in its
place. So then, right, I mean that's gonna get to the case
of the משנה, Mishna, as the גמרא Gemara says, אלא לרבא קשיא
מתניתין. ela leRava kashia matnitin. How do you explain the משנה? Mishna?
יד של עבד. Yad shel eved. We have this in the משנה
Mishna written on the slave's hand. נהי דלרבא ממתניתין לא קשיא. Nehi
delRava mimatnitin lo kashia. That's not difficult. בעדי מסירה ורבי אלעזר היא.
Be'eidei mesira veRabbi Eliezer hi. And that would also answer the answer
to our question here as well about whether you know it's given
over or not. The משנה Mishna could be talking about that there
were witnesses that it was given over, so you know it was
given over, you know what was written on it, it doesn't have
to be not forgeable because the witnesses read it. So the משנה
Mishna is fine. The case we're dealing with is a case that
you didn't see it given over and we're only relying on the
signatures. So before you get to the question of whether it was
actually given as a גט, get, you have to deal with the
question about whether it was forgeable and therefore not a good document
because nobody was there to see it being given over. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אלא לרמי בר חמא קשיא ela leRami Bar Chama
kashia because רמי בר חמא's Rami Bar Chama whole question was was
that there was no witnesses that it was given over. So the
גמרא Gemara says ולרמי בר חמא נמי לא קשיא. uleRami Bar Chama
nami lo kashia. That's not difficult.
בכתובת קעקע. Biksivos ka'aka. We're dealing with a tattoo, as Michael said.
Now of course the question is if we're dealing with a tattoo,
how are you allowed to do it? So maybe you're not allowed
to do it. But if you look at תוספות, Tosfot, but it
doesn't matter, it would still be a good גט. get. So if
you look at תוספות Tosfot דבכתובת קעקע, debiksivos ka'aka, מדאורייתא mide'oraisa תוספות
Tosfot says ליכא איסורא עד שיכתוב ויקעקע בדיו ובכחול כדתנן פרק ג'
דמכות. leika issura ad sheyichtov veyakake bedyo uvechachol kidenan perek gimmel deMakkos.
You might have to use certain types of inks and maybe here
you just did it without an ink at all, you know, or
maybe you did it with a different type of ink. ורבי שמעון
אומר אינו חייב אפילו כתובת קעקע עד שיכתוב את השם פירוש שם
עבודת כוכבים כמפורש שם בגמרא. veRabbi Shimon omer eino chayav afilu kesoves
ka'aka ad sheyichtov es hashem peirush shem avodas kochavim kimeforash sham bagemara.
Okay. ומיהו איסור דרבנן איכא הכא דהא אפילו אפר מקלה אסור ליתן
על גבי מכתו מפני שנראה ככתובת קעקע ואפילו איסור דרבנן. Umihu issur
derabbanan ika hacha deha afilu eifer mikleh assur liten al gabei makaso
mipnei shenireh kikesoves ka'aka veafilu issur derabbanan. ואפילו הוי הכא איסורא דאורייתא
מכל מקום הוי גט. veafilu havei hacha issura deoraisa mikol makom havei
get. It wouldn't stop it from being a גט get even if
you were over on an איסור issur of tattooing. Okay,
so anyway it was tattooed.
So that's how it's not forgeable.
Exactly. So anyway, it's definitely a- anyway- anyway so it's definitely a-
it's definitely a good גט, get, but the question is do you
know it was legitimately- it's not forgeable, but was it actually given
over did the slave just walk over? So the גמרא Gemara says
הכא במאי עסקינן hacha bemai askinan now that we're saying that that's
a scenario. מתניתין נמי לא תיקשי בכתב ידו *matnitin nami lo tikshi
bichtav yado* that could be the case of the משנה mishna? *Mishnah*.
You don't have to say there are witnesses in the משנה mishna
*Mishnah*. Anyway מאי הוה עלה *mai hava alah* what was the upshot?
Does that work? Can we assume that the slave was given over
if we didn't see the slave being given over? So תא שמע
tashma, *ta shema* come and hear דאמר ריש לקיש *d'amar Resh Lakish*
הגודות אין להם חזקה *hagodot ein lahem chazakah*. That there is no
חזקה *chazakah* on flocks. That if you basically a flock, the fact
that I'm in possession of your flock of
sheep maybe they were out grazing and your shepherd went home for
lunch or something and I took 'em or maybe they just walked
into my yard. So something that moves on its own
accord is not considered a normal sense of possession doesn't work. What
you have to do is you have to be... it's sort of
like קרקע *karka*. Well קרקע *karka* you can't be in possession because
you don't carry it around. So there there's not an idea of
possession because you don't actually possess it in the same way. And
what you need by קרקע *karka* to prove that it's yours if
you don't have an actual document and direct evidence is you need
to be on it for three years without being challenged. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says the same is true by something that does
move, but it actually could move by itself. The fact that's my
possession doesn't mean that I took possession. It might have come to
me. And that you only are considered to be able to prove
that it's yours if you don't have a direct like a bill
of sale if you actually
are in possession of it for three years.
So if I have a flock... not a קרקע *karka*, קרקע *karka*
doesn't move around, right? So if I have a flock even though
I've had it for two years and I haven't been challenged?
That's why you better hold on to your bill of sale for
three years. Yeah the same way the IRS asks you to hold
on to your receipts for three years.
Yeah and no one can prove anything really unless you have a
bill of sale.
Right or it's three years and then you don't have to keep
on holding on to it. So anyway so then the תוספות Tosefos
*Tosafot*'s question is
okay but then what was the ספק *safek*? I mean we know
that that's an established הלכה halacha *halachah* and it's even more obvious
by slaves that we say that slaves you don't have possession of
just by physically holding on to them that you need to have
some bill of sale. So what was the ספק *safek* here?
So תוספות Tosefos *Tosafot* says
well maybe the combination of the fact that it's in your possession
and that a גט get *get* is written on it those combined
should have somehow been evidence that it was given over as a
גט get. *get*. But anyway but for תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* the basic
question is is this actual type of a normal דיני ממונות dinei
mammonus *dinei mamonot* proof that you own it. Now the actual there's
a more interesting way of explaining this question which isn't just a
general דיני ממונות dinei mammonus *dinei mamonot*. It could be we always
knew that by flocks and slaves or whatever you needed a bill
of sale but here I think some ראשונים *Rishonim* I didn't check
but I'm pretty sure I remember some ראשונים *Rishonim* say the question
might be let's say even after
well you could sort of go two ways. You could sort of
say the question on the one hand could be remember we just
got through saying that you don't... it's not about taking monetary possession
of it. It can even be איסורי הנאה *issurei hana'ah* that don't
require that... it's not even possible to own possibly according to some
אחרונים *Acharonim* to own איסורי הנאה *issurei hana'ah*. So if that's true
what if you had something that you were in possession of but
not in a way that
demonstrated ownership? So is that still considered possession for a גט get
*get*? Now the answer could be
yes but at least but there's still the question of we don't
know factually what happened or not. Maybe yes if you're holding the
slave even if that doesn't demonstrate ownership in דיני ממונות dinei mamonot
*dinei mamonot* like that could still work as an act of receiving
your גט get *get*. It doesn't need to demonstrate ownership but now
we just don't know למעשה *lema'aseh* we don't know what happened. But
maybe the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*'s question is well maybe if we're not
dealing in a world of דיני ממונות dinei mamonot *dinei mamonot* in
the act of transfer maybe we're also not dealing with it in
the act of evidence and proof. And even if in דיני ממונות
dinei mamonus *dinei mamonot* purposes we would say possession of a slave
isn't proof by גט get *get* we're not dealing with חושן משפט
*Choshen Mishpat* we're dealing with אבן העזר *Even HaEzer* and we say
that the definition of proving that you have the גט get *get*
and it was given to you and you're proven to be divorced
is just the fact that physically it's in your property. Maybe it
doesn't go by the same הלכות *halachot* as דיני ממונות dinei mamonus
*dinei mamonot*. But that's one way of saying it. You could also
say the reverse. You could say that what would happen if a
woman had the גט get, *get* written on the slave and the
slave was in her possession for three years? Would she be divorced?
Because now she does prove that she owns it. Or could you
say no that even though from דיני ממונות mammonus *dinei mamonot* you're
proven to be owning the slave since it wasn't evident that it
was yours from the time it was
given since for the last three years you couldn't prove that this
slave was yours then that can't count as evidence that it was
given to you as a גט get, *get*. Evidence that it was
given to you as a גט get, *get* has to be something
that when you're in possession of it from the very beginning shows
that you're divorced not something that only three years later will we
now be able to realize actually. So part of I think what's
interesting about this question is that we're at the intersection of דיני
ממונות *dinei mamonot* and giving a גט get, *get*. What is the
act of giving a גט get. *get*? How much is the possession
of a גט get *get* as proof that you're divorced the same
as the standards of proof that you own something? And you could
go both ways. You could say that it could prove that it's
a גט get *get* even if it's not proved I own it
from דיני ממונות *dinei mamonot* or you could say after three years
maybe I own it דיני ממונות *dinei mamonot* but it still doesn't
work as a גט get *get*.
There's a question on this. I mean, so apparently the גמרא Gemara
felt it could be satisfied by this
answer, go to אין לכם חזקה, ein lachem chazaka, and that seems
to
be in that in their minds answering the גט get is not
a גט. get.
Right.
So according to that, it seems that it does feel that they
are that they are that that answer seems to be the way
I'm framing it, that it feels that the דיני ממונות is relevant
to it. And but it might be that the answer of אין
לכם חזקה ein lachem chazaka is more saying is is the phrasing
of it is more saying like you're not really even considered to
be in possession, and that's why it's an it cuts across both
categories.
But in essence what you're saying would have been no utility here?
Correct. בעי רמי בר חמא, Bai Rami bar Chama, whatever, he doesn't
have ממונות for that. בעי רמי בר חמא, Bai Rami bar Chama,
הרי מוחזקין בטבלא שלה, harei munchzakon betavla shela, הגט כתוב עליה. haget
katuv aleha.
So now here's a related question. You knew that he owned a
particular טבלא tabla and the גט get was written on it, והרי
היא יוצא מתחת ידו. ve-harei hi yotzei mitachas yado. And now the
husband is the guy's holding onto it. מהו? mahu? Now we don't
know, he hasn't given it to her yet. He just says I
want to give my wife this thing and divorce her with it.
Now he's in possession of it, so he's considered to be the
owner in דיני ממונות in all purposes. Why don't we let her
divorce? Because basically what's clear is she gave him this טבלא, tabla,
this you know tablet, she gave it to him for the purpose
that he could use it to write a גט get and give
it to her. But he has to own the גט get that
he's giving to her. So maybe there was not a full דעת
da'as to fully give it over since she knew she was going
to get it back anyway. It's like a classic question that rabbis
get which is we have this ring that we use, you know
that's been passed down from mother to daughter for many generations and
I'm getting married and I want my חתן chassan to give it
to me, can I give it to him that he should give
it to me for my wedding ring? Do we consider it that
you've really fully transferred ownership since you're expecting to get it back
anyway? So that's the question.
Yeah, but you'd have to do it in a way that it's
really serious. So the גמרא Gemara. says מי אמרינן, mi amrinan, do
we say אקנויי אקני ליה, akpuy akni lei, that she genuinely transferred
it to him? או דילמא, o dilma, do we say לא ידעה
לאקנויי? lo yada laknuya? Now תוספות Tosfos is a woman we'll see
why later, but anyway for now just לא ידעה לאקנויי. lo yada
laknuya. People don't know that they need to fully transfer something if
they're expecting to get it back. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, תא שמע,
come and hear. אף הוא העיד, Af hu heid, even he which
is which was I forget who he was, רבי יהודה בן בבא,
Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava, העיד heid על כפר קטן al kefar katan
שהיה בצד ירושלים, she-haya betzad Yerushalayim,
a little village that was by ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
והיה בו זקן אחד ve-haya bo zaken echad והיה מלוה לכל בני
הכפר. Vehaya malveh lechol benei hakfar, מלוה Malveh means accompany, right? How
would you say lend, מלוה? malveh? מלוה. Malveh. מלוה. Malveh. So their
heart so same thing as the loaner? Okay. והיה מלוה vehaya malveh
לכל בני הכפר, lechol benei hakfar. וכותב בכתב ידו. vechosev bichtav yado.
So he would lend to all people of the village and he
would write in his own handwriting, ואחרים חותמין, ve-acherim chosmin, and other
people would sign it. Which is fine, I mean obviously if you're
the lender, right, it's the guy who borrows which is his handwriting
substitutes for witnesses. The lender can't use his handwriting to substitute for
witnesses. So you get other people to witness it. But he would
be the guy, he'd prepare all the documents and get other witnesses
to sign. ובאו מעשה לפני חכמים והכשירו, U-va-u ma-aseh lifnei chachamim vehichshiru,
and the חכמים chachamim said it's fine.
ואמאי בעינן ספר מקנה וליכא? Ve-amai habinan sefer makneh veleika? Don't you
need that the document be owned by the one who is selling
the property? Now this isn't a sale, this is a loan, but
if you imagine if I'm selling Michael my field, right, and I
write on a piece of property, here I'll write on this ספר,
sefer, די מכורה לך di mechura lach and I give it to
him. So the point is that the one who is the one
who's going to be in possession of the document to prove that
he owns the field, right, it has to the document has to
be owned by the other side, by the side that's giving the
document over to be as evidence to that side. So in the
if you transfer that to a מלוה malveh לוה loveh scenario, okay,
that's just based on a פסוק, pasuk, okay? That's just the requirement.
Now if you transfer that to a מלוה malveh לוה loveh scenario,
okay, so the מלוה's malveh the one that's going to be in
possession of the document to prove that the guy owes him money.
So the idea of ספר מקנה sefer makneh there would mean the
לוה loveh who is also the one who is writing it like
the if you imagine if you were to write it actually in
his own hand it would be I owe you a hundred dollars
the same way I'm selling you my field, here take this document
I owe you a hundred dollars, here take this document, the document
has to be owned by the לוה loveh and given to the
מלוה. malveh. Now תוספות Tosafot questions that. תוספות Tosafot says you can
have this type of a formal requirement of ספר מקנה sefer makneh
when you're dealing with something that the actual שטר shtar is working
as an instrument to effect the transfer of property. But if all
the effect or a גט get. or a change of status or
whatever, you could say it has to be owned by the side
that is giving it over. But if all you're dealing with is
that it's going to prove that some an event happened that I
actually borrowed a hundred dollars, then why should there be a formal
requirement in terms of who owns the physical document, right? If the
document is actually effecting some change you could make these requirements of
what makes it into this instrument. But if it's just evidence and
witnesses are signing testimony who cares who owns the document? So תוספות
Tosafot says yeah you're right what we have to assume is that
we're not just talking about a מלוה malveh לוה. loveh. He's the
guy dealing with all the documents then presumably also when even people
came to sell him property, and maybe they sold him property to
pay off debts that they had from him or whatever, he would
also write their documents for them as well, that it really wouldn't
apply to a case of מלווה *malveh* and לווה *loveh*. But the
simple sense of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s
applying this idea of ספר מקנה Sefer Makneh *Sefer Makneh* across the
board, whether it's in שטר shtar קנין *Shtar Kinyan*, whether it's a
שטר *Shtar* that effects as an instrument, or whether it's a שטר
ראיה *Shtar Raya* where it's just evidence, it has to be owned
by the side that is giving it over. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says so why did that work? He owns these documents, but
it's the other side that's giving it to him. So presumably he
would prepare the document and then he'd say you want to borrow
$100 fine, he takes a sheet of paper, he writes out the
document, then he says here, take this, take possession of it, you
take possession of it, you get witnesses to sign and then you
give it back to him. So you see that you can assume
that somebody can do something properly to give over the document even
though he knows it's coming back to him. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says אלא לאו משום דאמרינן אקנויי אקני להו *Ella lav mishum
d'amrinan akneye aknei lehu* that he must transfer to the other side
even though he's getting it back. So here too the woman could
transfer the tablet to the other guy to the husband even though
she knows she's getting it back. So אמר רבא Amar Rava, מאי
קושיא *Amar Rava mai kushia* why is that difficult or why does
that prove anything? דילמא זקן שאני דידע לאקנויי *Dilma zaken shani de-yada
l'akneye* he says he was the elder and he knew and he
was the guy he was the literate person. So okay, he knew
what he had to do, that was his business anyway. It doesn't
mean that a woman knows that she's got to when we're not
just saying the fact that she's a woman, but a normal person
would know that you have to transfer the ownership fully even if
you're expecting to get it back. אלא אמר רב אשי מהכא *Ella
amar Rav Ashi mehacha*. ערב היוצא לאחר חיתום שטרות *Arev ha-yotze l'achar
chitum shtarot* if a co-signer a guarantor signs a document after it's
already been sealed and handed over. So I said
I owe Charlie $10,000 and I borrowed the money and I signed
the document and I gave it to Charlie. And now Charlie is
saying you know you didn't pay off whatever he's giving me a
hard time and I say you know what here I'm going to
get my friend David, he's going to co-sign that document for me
so you'll stop nudging me all the time. So David comes and
he signs it after it's already in Charlie's possession. That's הלכה *halacha*
ערב היוצא לאחר חיתום שטרות *arev ha-yotze l'achar chitum shtarot*. Okay, now
that works. Now the question is one minute, okay well let's take
a look. גובה מנכסים בני חורין *Goveh minechasim bnei chorin*. So Charlie
can now if he has to go collect from David, he can
collect from him although he can only collect from things that are
in David's property control, he can't collect from things that David has
sold because once the document was already registered before, people aren't going
to know that you are co-signed and since it won't be public
that you co-signed you the people that would purchase your property won't
be protected so he can Charlie can only collect from you directly,
he can't go ahead and collect from people that are you know
from people that purchased it from you already.
But why can he collect from yours at all? That wouldn't be
בני חורין *bnei chorin*.
No,
no, that would be בני חורין *bnei chorin*. Yeah, yeah, it's just
you can't do from things that have been sold. Now the thing
is but why can he collect from you at all? Why is
it a valid שטר *Shtar* as far as you're concerned? You weren't
in possession of it and gave it to him, he was in
possession of it. So again now the funny thing is since when
does an ערב *Arev* have to work from the property through a
שטר *Shtar*, like that's what תוספות Tosafos *Tosfos* discusses. Again, it's a
similar type of a question, maybe just by agreeing and maybe it's
a type of admission and anyway but the גמרא gemara *Gemara* is
assuming it works through normal שטר *Shtar* functions. So the only way
your signature created a שטר *Shtar* that now allows Charlie to collect
from you is if Charlie gave you back the שטר *Shtar* for
you to sign and for you to give it back to Charlie.
So again you see that you can trust somebody to do that.
So the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says אמר רב אשי מאי קושיא *Amar
Rav Ashi mai kushia* why is that difficult? דילמא גברא שאני דידע
לאקנויי *Dilma gavra shani de-yada l'akneye*. Now we get to the question
about women. Okay men, men know what they're doing in the world
of business, but a woman so here's what we really miss Rifka
you know there you can't assume that she knows you know that
she has to do. You could also say again that this is
maybe something that occurs you know maybe once in somebody's life getting
divorced, it's not something that people are well aware of or anyway,
hopefully we're not it's not a statement about women's innate capacity but
just about the fact they're not as involved in business as much
anyway. Okay so the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says like this, אלא אמר
רב אשי מהכא *Ella amar Rav Ashi mehacha* I'll give you a
case where even to even a case of a woman who knows
how to do it. מהכא אשה כותבת את גיטה *Mehacha isha kotevet
et Gittah* a woman can write her גט get *Get*, okay now
which means that the husband tells her you be my שליח shaliach
*Shaliach* to write you know to write the גט get, *Get* and
she goes ahead and writes the גט get, *Get*. ואיש כותב את
שוברו *V'ish kotev et shovro* and the man can write the
receipt. I Sarah received my כתובה *Kesuvah* from Reuven. Now of course
it's now it's now he's writing it but it's it doesn't mean
anything you can't write your own receipt unless witnesses have to sign
it and then she has to give it back to him the
same way she writes a גט get *Get*, it's not valid until
witnesses sign it and he gives it to her. But anyway they
can do the writing. שאין קיום הגט אלא בחותמיו *She-ein kiyum ha-Get
ella b'chotmav* it only becomes valid once it's signed. So anyway so
if that's so obvious that a woman can write her גט get.
*Get* what was the ספק *safek*? So תוספות Tosafos *Tosfos* says no
because the normal case I would have assumed that meant was here's
my quill, here's my paper, you just do the writing and it
doesn't prove the question of when the paper was owned by the
woman does she know to give transfer possession of it to the
man. But nevertheless... the גמרא gemara assumes that since it just says
סתם, stam, a woman can write the גט, get it means in
all cases, so that not only can she do the writing for
the man, but it's even if it's her parchment, we assume she
can transfer ownership, she will be able to know that he needs
to transfer ownership to her husband, that it has to be her
husband's parchment or after she finishes writing it she fully gives it
to the husband, so then the husband can give it back to
her.
And that's, and that's what's results based on? He...
Yeah, well, ספר מקנה Sefer Makneh. also, no, that the idea that
he has to own it is based on ספר מקנה. Sefer Makneh.
Why can't he just give it to her?
Well, because since again because because
we just because this gets back to the point that we don't
assume that דיני ממונות is necessarily the same as the act of
giving, right? That's what we've been dealing with from the very beginning,
that the act of giving doesn't necessarily mean being מקנה makneh something.
But the idea that he has to own it is learned from
the idea of ספר sefer. מקנה. makneh
So anyway, so that's, and all this is relevant exactly to that
question of can I give a ring for my חתן chosson to
give back to me? And the basic answer is yes, right? You
are, you know, you can go ahead write the שטר on your
own piece of paper or give the tablet to the guy or
even write the whole גט, get. and then you're trusted to fully
be מקנה makneh it over to your husband in order for the
husband to give it back to you.
Even if they didn't tell you, like this is what you need
to do, you just do it.
Well, I assume, I mean that's an interesting question which is that,
you know, which is I that seems to be the case of
the גמרא, gemara's which seems to be the exact question about whether
it's יד לאקנויה, yad le-aknoyeh, that somehow, which is a very good
point, meaning it's one thing to say you're right, it's one thing
to say here's the הלכתי halakhic requirement, do we believe you're doing
it בלב שלם? b'lev shalem? Right, part of the question of the
גמרא gemara seems to be do we even presume you knew what
you needed to do? And the answer seems to be yes. And
you're right, like that's a big question. Like forget the whole גמרא
אשה ידעה, Gemara ishah yad'ah, how many people would know that there's
a, it's one thing to know, oh everybody knows that the guy
has to own the ring and give it to the woman. But
how many people know that the guy has to own the document,
you know, as just to, rather than just hand over the document?
So that is the answer of the גמרא. gemara But you're right,
that's important to underscore, that's part of the חידוש. chiddush. Yes, Carly.
I think if Paula bought a ring and gave it to me
to give it to her under the חופה, chuppah, so
that's it, you're not married. Okay, go ahead. Yeah.
But more this would seem to imply more that it's the witnesses
rather than the actual writing itself that really matters for the, well,
it is. I mean, which is what we've been sort of learning.
Clearly, whether it's the signing of the witnesses or the presence of
the witnesses, right. So the גמרא gemara says like this, okay, now
that we're still with the slave, we're going to have another case.
אמר רבא, amar Rava, כתב לה גט ונתנו ביד עבדו וכתב לה
שטר מתנה עליו. katav lah get u-netano b'yad avdo ve-katav lah shtar
matanah alav. So now this is again, this is such a great
question because it goes to how much is the act of giving
of the גט, get the physical transfer of the object, or is
it taking possession? So on the one hand we've been saying you
don't need to take possession, on the other hand, I mean at
least in the case or or we might have been saying it
if he חסר הנאה chasar hana'ah the type of an object that
possession is not possible with. On the other hand, we've been saying
that the possession of the owner, of the husband, might hold back
if he says אני שלי. ani sheli. How about if the act
of taking possession is a little bit indirect? What does that mean?
What does it mean? Indirect. So he wrote a גט, get. now
here and he gave it to the slave, וכתב לה שטר מתנה
עליו, ve-katav lah shtar matanah alav, and then he gifted the slave
to the woman and he wrote a שטר מתנה shtar matanah about
the slave and she took possession of the שטר מתנה. shtar matanah.
So she did not actually take possession directly of the גט. get,
She took possession of the slave in which the גט get was,
or so you could say the act of נתינה, netinah, the act
of the physical giving of the גט get, was given, it was
put on his חצר chatzer if we consider the slave his חצר.
chatzer. Let's imagine for example that it isn't a slave. I put
this גט get, down and I put it in my yard, and
then I sell my wife my yard. Okay, so you could say
well there was a giving of a גט get. which wasn't to
my wife, and there was a taking possession of it which was
something which was like, which was, you know, which was not the
same as the act of giving. We're breaking up the taking possession
and giving into two separate things that it has to be, he
gives it to her, not that she goes and takes it.
Well, okay, so there's the active part that she's doing as well,
but even before we get to her active part, okay, maybe the
act is you know, if you focus on the act of giving
as the physical act, there was no act of giving, there was
just an act of taking, there was an act of giving which
wasn't her, and an act of taking possession which wasn't an act
of giving. Or maybe you could say the actual fact that I
am giving her the
the field and she's taking possession of the field, that becomes the
act of giving of the גט. get, It's like it's all in
one big package, right? It's the גט get, with the field that
I'm giving her. So that seems to be the גמרא's gemara assumption
that that would work. Michael's point about the fact that she's taking
an active role we'll get to in a minute. So that's why
the גמרא gemara doesn't ask the case in the case of a
field. So what's special about the case of a slave? Let's take
a look. So it says like this, okay, כתב לה גט ונתנו
ביד עבדו וכתב לה שטר מתנה עליו קנתהו ומתגרשת בו. katav lah
get u-netano b'yad avdo ve-katav lah shtar matanah alav k'natahu u-mitgareshet bo.
It works, she takes possession of the slave and she's divorced. So
the גמרא gemara says ואמאי חצר מהלכת היא? ve-amai chatzer mehalekhet hi?
What, is that our משנה? mishna Well, our משנה Mishnah. might, no,
our משנה is that the גט get the the slave is the
גט get, and he directly transferred the slave, right? So here he's
actually transferring the thing that the slave is on, he's actually... He's
actually transferring the slave, the slave is holding the גט. get Okay,
the גט get is being held in the hand of the slave,
so you might say that's not an act of giving a גט,
get it's an act of giving a slave. Okay, no, קנתהו ומסתגרשת
בו. knaso umistagareshet bo. והא אמאי, veha amai, why is this true?
חצר מהלכת היא, chatzer mehalechet hee, וחצר מהלכת לא קנה. vechatzer mehalechet
lo kana. So again, like the גמרא gemara by גודרות, godros, rather
than from our perspective where the חידוש chiddush is what defines an
act of giving a גט, get. the גמרא Gemara wants to ask
a דיני ממונות question, which is, is that you don't take possession
of a slave, a slave, the idea that if, if something you
own is in your field, you take possession of it, that's a
קנין חצר. kinyan chatzer. How if something is on my slave's body,
do I take possession of it because I own my slave? So
that's like a קנין חצר. kinyan chatzer. But the problem is that
the slave, as we sort of mentioned before about slaves, is that
they move around. And therefore the idea that my חצר chatzer takes
possession of something for me is only if my חצר chatzer is
stable. If I have a moving חצר, chatzer, if it's מהלכת, mehalechet,
okay, because it's not, it's for whatever reason, it's not seen as
a classic חצר, chatzer, and therefore things that are in my חצר
מהלכת chatzer mehalechet do not become mine. So the גמרא Gemara is
not bothered about the הלכה that it's a נתינת גט. nesinat get.
Fine, it's a נתינת גט. nesinat get. But she doesn't own the
piece of paper because something in the hand of a slave doesn't
get owned by somebody, it's a חצר מהלכת. chatzer mehalechet.
Okay, unless you put the slave in her חצר, chatzer, and then
it would, then it would work.
Yeah, but if basically let's say it was her slave, the גמרא
Gemara is saying, to put a גט get in the hand of
the slave of a woman wouldn't work because it's a חצר מהלכת.
chatzer mehalechet. Okay, that's the גמרא's Gemara problem. So the גמרא Gemara
says,
והא עומד, veha omed, right?
So that was going to be the answer. Okay. וחצר מהלכת לא
קנה. vechatzer mehalechet lo kana. וכי תימא בעומד, vechi teima b'omed, let's
say he happens to be standing at this moment? והא אמר רבא:
veha amar rava: כל שאילו מהלך לא קנה, עומד ויושב לא קנה.
kol she'ilu mahalech lo kana, omed ve'yoshev lo kana. No, since it
wouldn't work if he was moving, it doesn't work if he's standing.
So forget the fact that first it was all his and then
he whatever. Even if directly it's her slave, shouldn't work. It doesn't
work with קנין חצר. kinyan chatzer. So the גמרא Gemara... says, והוא
שכפות. v'hu shekafus. Fine, the slave is bound, so he's not moving.
Alright. ואמר רבא, ve'amar rava, but of course then the גמרא Gemara
just deals with that side problem, it ignores the bigger חידוש, chiddush,
which is that there was no direct giving of the גט. get
So you have to, what you have to do is you have
to look at the giving of the עבד eved who's holding the
גט get is considered like one big package that is basically defines
an act of giving of the גט. get. But we're going to
continue to clarify. ואמר רבא, ve'amar rava, Rava also says: כתב לה
גט ונתנו בחצרו, וכתב לה שטר מתנה עליו. kasav lah get venasno
b'chatzeiro, vechasav lah shtar matana alav. You wrote a גט get? and
you put it in his חצר, chatzer, okay, which is like his
עבד, eved, so and then you wrote a שטר מתנה shtar matana
on it, קנתהו ומסתגרשת בו. knaso umistagareshet bo. That works. Now that's
a much simpler case and that clearly the חידוש chiddush is not
about מהלכת, mehalechet, the חידוש chiddush is the fact that that constitutes
an act of giving a גט. get So the גמרא Gemara says
וצריכא, utzricha, you need both. אי אשמעינן עבד, ei ashmi'inan eved, if
it said a slave, הוה אמינא דוקא עבד, hava amina davka eved,
אבל חצר לגזור, aval chatzer ligzor, that it works by a slave,
but it doesn't work by a חצר. chatzer. Why? משום חצרה הבאה
לאחר מכאן. mishum chatzeirah haba'ah le'achar mikan. What happens if she gets
the field afterwards? Now what do you mean? This is a case
where she gets the field afterwards and it works. So רש"י rashi
says it means a third party. I write my wife a גט,
get I put it in my, in my yard, I sell my
yard to Michael and then Michael sells the yard with still has
the גט get in it to my wife. Okay, so that obviously
wouldn't work because yes, there she clearly she is taking possession of
the physical piece of paper but clearly there's no act of נתינת
הגט, nesinat haget, okay, if it's coming through a third party. So
you might think that that case we won't allow because it'll lead
people allowing a case of coming through a third party. So it
had to tell you we allow that. Okay. ואי אשמעינן חצר, ve'ei
ashmi'inan chatzer, if it just had the case of חצר, chatzer, הוה
אמינא דוקא חצר, hava amina davka chatzer, אבל עבד לגזור כפות אטו
שאינו כפות. aval eved ligzor kafus atu she'eino kafus. I would have
said I won't allow the slave case because the slave case, if
we allow it when the slave is bound, we'll allow it when
he's not bound. קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that we allow
both cases. But nevertheless, the big חידוש chiddush we're not exploring yet,
but it's about to explore, is besides that we don't make גזירות,
gezeirot, is that this is all considered an act of giving a
גט, get it's all like one big package. Now why is that
a חידוש? chiddush? On the one hand you could say the חידוש
chiddush is because I'm not really being directly מקנה makneh the גט,
get I'm being
מקנה
the חצר chatzer and the קניין הגט kinyan haget comes indirectly through
that, okay, so that's maybe a piece of it. But now but
what the גמרא Gemara focuses on is what Michael said, which is
that she has to take an active part of taking possession of
the חצר, chatzer, which isn't true by an act of giving a
גט. get. A giving of a גט, get she could be totally
passive. Here she has to be a willing participant in taking possession
of the חצר chatzer or of the slave. So let's take a
look. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: אמר אביי: amar abaye: מכדי, michdi, let's take a look. חצר
מהיכא איתרבאי? chatzer meheicha itrabai? How do you know that a חצר
chatzer works? מידה, miyada, the same way it says ונתן בידה, venasan
beyadah, her hand. So we say her חצר, chatzer, her field counts
like her hand. But one minute: מה ידה דאיתא בין מדעתה בין
בעל כרחה, mah yadah de'isa bein meda'atah bein be'al korcha, when it
comes to giving of a גט, get if you give it to
her person, it's whether she agrees or doesn't agree. אף חצרה דאיתא
בין מדעתה בין בעל כרחה. af chatzeirah de'isa bein meda'atah bein be'al
korcha. So when you put it in her yard, it should have
to be something similar. She already owns the yard and whether she
likes it or not, you put the גט get in her yard
and she's divorced, okay, as opposed to this case והמתנה, vehamatana, this
case of the gift, מדעתה איתא בעל כרחה ליתא. meda'atah isa be'al
korcha leisa. It'll only work if she agrees to accept the gift
of the yard or the gift of the slave. Okay, so basically
what the גמרא Gemara is saying then you
could
say... An act of giving a gift fundamentally has to be a
unilateral act. Okay, whereas this right, could agree but it's irrelevant, whereas
this act fundamentally requires her active participation and therefore maybe it's not
defined as an act of giving a gift. That's a really good
question. Okay, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara. says. So מתיב
ליה רב אשי מבר אבשיא Mativ lo Rav Ashi mi-bar Avshaya or
רב שימי בר אשי Rav Shimi bar Ashi asked this: והא שליחות
לקבלה דמדעתה איתא בעל כרחה ליתא דהוי שליח לקבלה. ve-ha shlichut le-kabbalah
de-midaatah itah baal korchah leita de-havei shaliach le-kabbalah. Abaye says that there
are other cases where the act where where where the act requires
her active participation. If she makes an agent to receive her גט,
get. okay, then that requires her to agree and presumably if while
the גט get is being given she's
saying no no no I don't agree I don't agree, then the
שליחות shlichut ends and the גט and the giving of the גט
was no good. So שליחות shlichut only works if she's actively agreeing
throughout the process and nevertheless it constitutes an extension of her and
it constitutes a good act of giving of the גט. Okay, so
that's a good so you see that that can be okay.
בכהאי גוונא שליח לקבלה. be-khai gavna shaliach le-kabbalah. And אביי Abaye and
אביי Abaye would say back אטו שליחות מידא איתרבאי? atu shlichut mi-yada
itrabai? שליחות shlichut is not an idea of her hand. משלח ושלחה
איתרבאי. mi-veshalach ve-shilchah itrabai. It's based on a different פרשה parsha that
you can it says he shall send her from the house but
from the word שלח shalach we learn that he can make an
agent. So אביי Abaye says is yes there are times where it
does an act does require her active agreement at least to the
framework and the setting and the setup, okay, but that's based on
a פרשה parsha of שליחות. shlichut. This is not the idea of
the field is not a פרשה parsha of שליחות shlichut and therefore
it's not clear it would work the same way. Another way to
conceptualize it is the following: by the case of the שליחות shlichut
she had to agree to making the person her שליח shaliach and
maybe implicitly to keeping the person her שליח shaliach? but the actual
act of giving right is not is still a unilateral act. Once
she set up the arrangement it's still a unilateral act of the
act of giving whereas in the case of transferring the field that
has the גט in it the act of giving cannot take place
it can never get to her without her actively agreeing and participating
and taking you know and taking possession. So it really is of
a different quality although again the גמרא Gemara is sort of focusing
I'm focusing on the act of giving the גמרא is focusing on
the sort of is this thing considered a יד yad or is
it a שליח? shaliach. א שליח shaliach works מדעתה midaatah but for
it to work as a יד yad it has to be functional
even שלא מדעתה shelo midaatah and that's not true here.
So the גמרא still works it out.
I mean but that's the challenge, why should it? So the גמרא
says like this ואיבעית אימא ve-iba'it eima and if you want to
say שליחות לקבלה נמי אשכחן בעל כרחה, shlichut le-kabbalah nami ashkachan baal
korchah, okay that you know what a שליחות לקבלה shlichut le-kabbalah also
can work sometimes בעל כרחה. baal korchah. Where does a שליחות לקבלה
shlichut le-kabbalah work against her will? שכן אב מקבל גט לבתו קטנה
בעל כרחה. she-ken av mekabbel get le-vito ktana baal korchah. A husband
a father can accept a גט for his daughter against her will
and תוספות Tosafos by the way points out that it would even
be against could even be against the father's will. A person can
give a גט to a father against his will against her will
and he's considered to be a שליח. shaliach. Okay so therefore and
that's why if the institution works בעל כרחה baal korchah it'll work
when she actively appoints a שליח. shaliach So תוספות Tosafos says okay
but then say the same thing here. If I own the חצר
chatzer if if my wife owns the חצר chatzer it works בעל
כרחה baal korchah
right? So then בעל כרחה baal korchah בעל כרחה baal korchah so
then we should be okay with it working when she has to
take active possession of the חצר. chatzer. Right? The same way we
say well if the institution of שליחות shlichut works in some cases
בעל כרחה baal korchah בעל כרחה baal korchah
it should work even when she's willing. So okay say the same
thing here. תוספות Tosafos says no there's a difference because
the case of the חצר chatzer she could always in theory divest
herself of the חצר. chatzer. So there's always even when the חצר
chatzer works בעל כרחה baal korchah there's a way in which in
theory she could divest that relationship as opposed to the father and
the daughter that is a hundred percent you know and there's no
way anybody can get out of that. And therefore what we're saying
is one way or another we understand that שליחות shlichut can work
even when she needs to be a active participant if she need
to appoint a שליח shaliach even because it's a different פרשה parsha
or she's already set up the the the thing or because there's
an example of it that works completely against her will. So the
fact that it works שליחות shlichut when she has to actively appoint
a שליח shaliach is one thing but we're not prepared to accept
that necessarily this חידוש chiddush of רבא Rava is true because this
חידוש chiddush of רבא Rava is a big חידוש chiddush in the
case where she's needed at the time of the giving to be
an active participant in taking possession a willing participant in taking possession
of the object okay and that is something that we normally never
find by a גט. שליחות shlichut is a different story but certainly
without a שליח being present the whole idea is that it's unilateral
and in רבא's Rava case it's not unilateral so the גמרא... גמרא
is not necessarily willing to go along with רבא's Rava חידוש.
chiddush. Okay, so we hope.
Now, how do you know?
I'm looking at just what the רמב"ם, Rambam, yeah, the little ד
daled by אמר רבא, Rava, כותב את הגט ונתנו על ידו או
על זרועו, או כותב על שטר ונתנו על
ידו או על זרועו כמאן דפטורה מגופיה בה.
kotev et ha-get venasno al yado o al zeroo, o kotev al
shetar unnasno
al
yado o al zeroo kman depatara migufeih bah. All right, well I
have to look at the רמב"ם Rambam but whatever it is, אביי
Abaye certainly isn't happy. Okay, so I don't know,
אביי Abaye and רבא, Rava right?
Okay, fine, you're right. Okay, which is, so I mean, I didn't
check the רמב"ם, Rambam, you're probably right, but אביי Abaye raises a
really good question. And what you see is that that's רבא's Rava
חידוש. chiddush. רבא's Rava חידוש chiddush is that that constitutes an act
of נתינה. nesina. So what you have to appreciate is what the
גמרא is doing here along the lines is that it's exploring the
intersection or the relationship between the act of נתינה nesina and the
act of taking possession, you know, of a דיני ממונות type of
a taking of possession. And רבא Rava. set up a case where
it really only works through a דיני ממונות taking possession, which on
the one hand is a חידוש chiddush that we bundle it and
we look at it as an act of נתינה, nesina, but on
the other hand it's a חידוש chiddush that it works even though
she needs to be an active participant. Yes.
I just wondered since space is where we rule by אביי ורבא.
Abaye ve-Rava. Well we don't rule like אביי Abaye in יע"ל קג"ם.
Yaal Kagam. Yeah, I mean so I mean I think Michael is
right, I didn't check but I think Michael's right that we rule
like רבא. But it's still worth appreciating the nature of the challenge.
Right, and she could, she could refuse. Yeah, but if she does
accept, it's a חידוש chiddush that it works even though it's a
different nature of an act.
So if she refused, like I'll take the חצר chatzer and not
the גט?
No, it's all, unless he's okay with it. Okay, על עלה של
זית. ala shel zayis. Let's read, let's at least turn the page.
בשלמא יד דעבד לא אפשר למקטעיה אלא קרן של פרה ליקטעיה. Bishlama
yad de-eved lo efshar le-miktayei ela keren shel para le-miktayei. So why,
it says if you write on the hand of the slave, you
give over the slave. You write on the horn of a cow,
you give over the cow. So it says I get why you
don't cut off the hand of the slave, because you're not allowed
to. Okay, but why don't you just, but why does it sound
like you can't cut off the horn of the cow? What would
be the problem of cutting off the horn of a cow? So
the גמרא says, וליתבה לה. ve-leisva lah. So אמר קרא, amar kra,
וכתב ונתן לה. ve-kasav ve-nasan lah. מי שאינו מחוסר אלא כתיבה ונתינה,
יצא זה שמחוסר כתיבה קציצה ונתינה. Mi she-eino mechusar ela kesiva ve-nesina,
yatza zeh she-mechusar kesiva ketzitza ve-nesina. Something that only requires giving over,
not something that requires cutting and giving over. Now the funny thing
is, is that it didn't require cutting, right? You could have given
over the whole cow, you just chose to cut. So the question
is, what constitutes מחוסר קציצה? mechusar ketzitza? And תוספות Tosafos has a
whole discussion about what if you had a גט that you want
to like trim the edges off of. Says, well first of all
that's clearly not a problem. That's just, you know, some trivial cutting.
If it's not cutting from a main larger thing, you're just cutting
off some side, some trivial stuff, that's not an issue. But תוספות
says that there was a case where they wrote a גט on
a large piece of paper and the גט was only a small
part of it, and they cut away, the גט was a minority,
and they cut away the גט and then gave the גט. Okay,
and that actually was a big מחלוקת machlokas תוספות says of, you
know, the בעלי התוספות baalei hatosafos whether that was a כשר kasher
גט or not. Is that considered מחוסר קציצה? mechusar ketzitza? Because from
the גמרא it makes it sound, normally מחוסר קציצה mechusar ketzitza would
be a case where a קציצה ketzitza was necessary. The גמרא makes
it sound like even if it wasn't necessary, even if you just
did a קציצה ketzitza it would be a problem, if you cut
it away from something major. And תוספות says well maybe we'll limit
it to cases where the major thing that you cut it away
from was something that was a live animal or מחובר mechubar or
growing thing. Right because that's the cases about like, you know, we'll
see later about cutting something that's growing from the ground. That would
be considered a major change. You took something from something living and
organic and you basically made it like you plucked a leaf, you
ripped out a leaf of the tree when it was attached and
then you plucked it off. So you made a major transformation of
the object. It was part of a living growing organic thing and
now you've made it this like, you know, this inanimate thing. Or
you cut off the horn of a cow from a living cow.
Okay but if you cut off paper from paper, even from a
huge piece of paper, it would not be a big deal. Okay,
but that's what he's inclined to say, but he leaves it as
a question whether such a גט actually would have been good or
not. All right, a more even a more limiting approach would be
saying that it's only no good when it was necessary to cut
it off. But it doesn't sound that way from the גמרא. It
sounds like the very act of cutting it would have been a
problem. Let's just, I know it's 8:30 if you have to go,
but I would just want to read to the משנה. It'll go
very fast. רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר. Rabbi Yose HaGlili omer. רבי יוסי
הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili says you cannot write a גט on בעלי
חיים. baalei chayim. Okay, so מאי טעמא דרבי יוסי הגלילי? mai taama
d'Rabbi Yose HaGlili? דתניא. detanya. That
he can't even give her the cow. ספר. sefer? It says וכתב
לה ספר כריתות. ve-kasav lah sefer krisus. אין לי אלא ספר, ein
li ela sefer, I only know like a scroll. מנין לרבות כל
דבר? minayin lerabbos kol davar? Anything? תלמוד לומר וכתב לה, Talmud lomar
ve-kasav lah, מכל מקום. mikol makom. Anything. אם כן מה תלמוד לומר
ספר? Im kein mah talmud lomar sefer? מה ספר דבר שאין בו
רוח חיים ואינו אוכל, Mah sefer davar she-ein bo ruach chayim ve-eino
ochel, something that is not living and that's not
food, אף כל דבר שאין בו רוח חיים ואינו אוכל. af kol
davar she-ein bo ruach chayim ve-eino ochel. Because like who says that's
what you're going to exclude based on ספר? sefer So I just
have to show you there's one line in תוספות where תוספות says,
if you see תוספות מה ספר דבר שאין בו רוח חיים, Tosafos
mah sefer davar she-ein bo ruach chayim, go two lines down directly
on almost under the words מה, mah, it says ועוד דהכל כפי
מה שדימו לו החכמים, לא ככל אחד עין הראוי לו. ve-od de-hakol
lefi mah she-dimu lo hachachamim, lo ke-chol achad ein ha-raui lo. It's
all up to the sages to decide that when we have to
say it has to be similar to x, you know, what's a
relevant point of similarity. It's all contextual and the sages get to
decide in each case. So here they decided the thing that's most
different from a scroll are animals and food. Okay, so anyway... מה
ספר דבר שאין בו רוח חיים ואינו אוכל, ma sefer davor she-ein
bo ruach chaim ve-eino ochel, כל דבר שאין בו רוח חיים ואינו
אוכל. kol davor she-ein bo ruach chaim ve-eino ochel. It can't be
animals or food. For רבנן, Rabbanan, the Rabbis who don't have that
limit would say אם כתב בספר im katav b'seifer in a book,
in a scroll, כי דקאמרי ki dekamri the word ספר sefer would
have meant a scroll and we would have limited the objects. השתא
דכתיב ספר, hashta dechtiv sefer, it doesn't mean a scroll, וספר דברים
בעלמא הוא דקאמר, vesefer devarim be'alma hu deka'amar, it means a story,
a narrative. It doesn't mean a scroll, so we're not limiting the
physical objects. For
רבנן, Rabbanan, האי וכתב מאי עביד ליה, hai vechatav mai avid leh,
which רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda used to say comes to include a
wide range and not just actual scrolls? But the Rabbis don't have
any limit of the object, so what do they need וכתב vechatav
to tell you, which is a funny question? מיבעי להו בכתיבה מתגרשת
ואינה מתגרשת בכסף mibei lehu bechtiva mitgareshet ve'eina mitgareshet bekesef to tell
you only with a script and not you can't give money as
a גט. סלקא דעתך אמינא איקש הוויה ליציאה, salka da'atach amina ikash
havaya litsia, divorce is connected to marriage. מה הוויה בכסף אף יציאה
נמי בכסף, ma havaya bekesef af yetsia nami bekesef, the same thing
marriage is with money so maybe divorce is money. קמשמע לן וכתב
kamashma lan vechatav and only if it's written. Because if ספר sefer
already means a script, why do you need the word וכתב? vechatav?
Of course, there's a lot of things we learn from וכתב. vechatav.
Anyway, ואידך, ve'idach, and how about רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, where did
he learn that from? נפקא ליה מספר כריתות. nafka leh misefer kritut.
A book of divorce. ספר כרתה ואין דבר אחר כרתה, sefer karata
ve'ein davor acher karata, only a book creates a divorce, not something
else. ואידך, ve'idach, what do the Rabbis do with ספר כריתות? sefer
kritut?
Or the word כריתות kritut presumably, מיבעי ליה דבר הכורת בינו לבינה.
mibei leh davor hakoret beino leveina.
It has to create a complete severance. כדתניא הרי זה גיטך על
מנת שלא תשתי יין על מנת שלא תלכי לבית אביך
לעולם. kidtanya harei ze gittech al menat shelo tishti yayin al menat
shelo telchi leveit avich le'olam. If here's a גט on a condition
that's for forever, that you don't drink wine or you don't go
to your father's house, אין זה כריתות. ein ze kritut. It's not
good because it doesn't sever. עד שלושים יום הרי זה כריתות, ad
shloshim yom harei ze kritut, for thirty days it is good.
Afterwards? Or even in the middle?
No, immediately, as long as she keeps by the condition. ואידך ve'idach
and the other would say, how do you get that idea that
it has to be completely severed? מכרית כריתות. mikrit kritut. It could
have said ספר כרית sefer karit and it says ספר כריתות. sefer
kritut. That tells you it has to be fully severed. ואידך כרית
כריתות לא דרשי. ve'idach karit kritut lo darshi. The other doesn't learn
it from that. Anyway, so we learn from one of them basically
learns from the idea of ספר limiting the physical objects, it can't
be animals and food, and the other doesn't limit that, but does
have a limit that it cannot be מחוסר קציצה. mechusar ketsitsa. And
what is considered מחוסר קציצה, mechusar ketsitsa, as I said, is a
question. Does it mean only when קציצה ketsitsa is necessary? The גמרא
sounds like it's no, even just doing קציצה ketsitsa would be a
problem. But what type of קציצה? ketsitsa? So it says a trivial
thing, like trimming off some minor thing, is not an issue, but
trimming off something big from something large could be. And the question
is is that anything, or only when you're taking something from something
that's alive and growing, is that considered like a real change that
would actually be a problem? Okay, so we will end with this,
at least.